

COMPUTATIONAL SCIENTIST · APPLIED MATHEMATICIAN

San Francisco, California

☐ +1 510-388-2095 | ☑ daancamps@gmail.com | 🏕 campsd.github.io | ☑ campsd | 🛅 campsd | 🕏 Daan Camps

Dated: May 22, 2024.

Staff member in Advanced Technologies Group at NERSC working on integrating quantum technologies with future HPC systems. Previously, computational mathematics postdoctoral researcher at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory with a broad scientific interest and a passion for problem-solving. Almost 5 years research experience in quantum information and quantum algorithms, 9+ years experience in computational mathematics, and 2+ years experience as project engineer. Recent collaborations resulted in a robust publication record.

Work Experience

NERSC, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory

Berkeley, USA

COMPUTER SYSTEMS ENGINEER/HPC ARCHITECTURE AND PERFORMANCE ENGINEER IN ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES GROUP

Apr. 2022 - Current

- Working on integrating HPC with future quantum technologies,
- Benchmarking of heterogeneous quantum-classical systems,
- Developing and driving NERSC's quantum computing program and strategy,
- Research on quantum algorithms for scientific computing.

Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory

Berkeley, USA

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER IN COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS

Nov. 2019 - Apr. 2022

- Research on quantum information and quantum algorithms with a focus on circuit compilation and synthesis,
- Completed projects on Hamiltonian simulation, quantum chemistry, quantum linear algebra, and quantum image processing,
- Software engineering of nonlinear tensor factorization package,
- Developed QCLAB, QCLAB++, F3C, F3C++, QPIXL++ and FunFact, FABLE,
- Team scientist.

KU Leuven, Belgium

TEACHING ASSISTANT Sep. 2015 - Jun. 2019

- Exercise sessions for courses on numerical modeling and approximation, numerical mathematics,
- Mentor of master student projects.

IPCOS NV Leuven, Belaium

PROJECT ENGINEER IN DIGITAL OILFIELD TEAM

Aug. 2013 - Sep. 2015

- Deployment and maintenance of upstream production monitoring models based on real-time process data,
- Development and deployment of new data-driven pipeline leak detection models,
- Customer-oriented role: presenting on-site training sessions and providing end user support.

Skills, Competencies & Training.

Programming

- MATLAB, C++, Python, Fortran 90.
- OpenMP and MPI.
- git, CMake
- QCLAB and QCLAB++: quantum circuit development, analysis and simulation.
- F3C and F3C++: fast and scalable quantum circuit compilation for Hamiltonian simulation.

Open source projects

- QPIXL++: efficient and compressible representations for quantum images.
- FunFact: tensor algebra and deep learning via Einstein notations.
- FABLE: generate quantum circuits for block encodings.

Research interests

Quantum algorithms, Scalable quantum benchmarking, Quantum circuit synthesis, Numerical linear algebra, Tensor decomposition techniques, Manifold optimization, Eigenvalue problems, Randomized algorithms, Scientific machine learning,

• Communications Excellence (Haas Business School, UC Berkeley, 2023)

Formal training

- Mathematics of Big Data: Sketching and (Multi-)Linear Algebra (MSRI Graduate Summer School, 2021)
- Fundamentals of Machine Learning (SOCN Graduate School, 2018)
- Low-Rank Tensor Techniques (Haussdorff School, 2016)

Personal & Communication

Languages

- Dutch: NativeEnglish: Fluent
- French: Moderate
- TA for B.Sc. courses on numerical modeling and approximation, numerical mathematics at KU Leuven.

Teaching

- Mentor of M.Sc. thesis projects at KU Leuven.
- Mentor of summer interns at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory.
- Mentor of postdoctoral researchers at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory.

Publications & Preprints

Evaluation of the classical hardware requirements for large-scale quantum computations,

- 2024 Camps D., Rrapaj E., Klymko K., Austin B., Wright N.J. Proceedings of ISC-HPC24 Conference, DOI:10.23919/ISC.2024.10528937
 - Long-lived oscillations of false and true vacuum states in neutral atom systems, Darbha S.,
- 2024 Kornjača M., Liu F., Balewski J., Hirsbrunner M. R., Lopes P., Wang S., Van Beeumen R., Klymko K., Camps D. arXiv:2404.12371.
 - False vacuum decay and nucleation dynamics in neutral atom systems, Darbha S., Kornjača
- 2024 M., Liu F., Balewski J., Hirsbrunner M. R., Lopes P., Wang S., Van Beeumen R., Camps D., Klymko K. arXiv:2404.12360.
- **Engineering quantum states with neutral atoms,** Balewski J., Kornjača M., Klymko K., Darbha S., Hirsbrunner M. R., Lopes P., Liu F., Camps D. arXiv:2404.04411.
- 2024 Explicit Quantum Circuits for Block Encodings of Certain Sparse Matrices, Camps D., Lin L., Van Beeumen R., Yang C., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 45(1)DOI:10.1137/22M1484298, arXiv:2203.10236.

 Quantum-parallel vectorized data encodings and computations on trapped-ions and
- **transmon QPUs**, Balewski J., Amankwah M., Van Beeumen R., Bethel E., Perciano T., Camps D. Scientific Reports, DOI: 10.1038/s41598-024-53720-x, arXiv:2301.07841.
- **Efficient Quantum Trace Estimation with Reconfigurable Real-Time Circuits**, Shen Y., Klymko K., Rabani E., Camps D., Van Beeumen R., Lindsey M. arXiv:2401.04176.
- 2024 Simulating dirty bosons on a quantum computer, Bassman Oftelie L., Van Beeumen R., Camps D., de Jong W., Dupont M., New Journal of Physics, DOI:10.1088/1367-2630/ad1a2d, arXiv:2210.08386.
- 2023 *k-Commutatitivity and Measurement Reduction for Expectation Values*, DelFavero B., Sarkar R., Camps D., Sawaya N., LaRose R. arXiv:2312.11840.
- 2023 *Quantum-centric Supercomputing for Materials Science: A Perspective on Challenges and Future Directions*, arXiv:2312.09733.
 - A Performance Model for Estimating the Cost of Scaling to Practical Quantum Advantage,
- 2023 Camps D., Klymko K., Austin B., Wright N. J., A, Proceedings of the SC '23 Workshops of The International Conference on High Performance Computing, Network, Storage, and Analysis, DOI:10.1145/3624062.3625533.
 - Efficient Quantum Counting and Quantum Content-Addressable Memory for DNA
- **2023** *similarity*, Balewski J., Camps D., Klymko K., Tritt A, 2023 IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE), DOI:10.1109/QCE57702.2023.00050, arXiv:2308.00699. *HamLib: A library of Hamiltonians for benchmarking quantum algorithms and hardware*,
- 2023 Sawaya N., Marti-Dafcik D., Ho Y., Tabor D., Bernal D., Magann A., Premaratne S., Dubey P., Matsuura A., de Jong W., Benjamin S., Parekh O., Tubman N., Klymko K., Camps D. arXiv:2306.13126.

- Estimating Eigenenergies from Quantum Dynamics: A Unified Noise-Resilient
- **2023** *Measurement-Driven Approach*, Shen Y., Camps D., Darbha S., Szasz A., Klymko K., Williams-Young D., Tubman N., Van Beeumen R. arXiv:2306.01858.
 - Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits: Particle Creation, Arbitrary
- **2023** *Lattices and Controlled Evolution*, Kökcü E., Camps D., Bassman Oftelie L., de Jong W., Van Beeumen R., Kemper A. arXiv:2303.09538.
- 2023 *QCLAB++: Simulating Quantum Circuits on GPUs*, Van Beeumen R., Camps D., Mehta N. arXiv:2303.00123.
 - Exploring Finite Temperature Properties of Materials with Quantum Computers, Powers C.,
- **2023** Bassman Oftelie L., Camps D., de Jong W. A., Scientific Reports, DOI: 10.1038/s41598-023-28317-5, arXiv:2205.00081.
 - FABLE: Fast Approximate Quantum Circuits for Block-Encodings, Camps D., Van Beeumen R.
- 2022 IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE), DOI: 10.1109/QCE53715.2022.00029, arXiv:2205.00081.
 - Quantum pixel representations and compression for N-dimensional images, Amankwah M.
- 2022 G., Camps D., Bethel E.W., Van Beeumen R., Perciano T. Scientific Reports, DOI: 10.1038/s41598-022-11024-y.
 - Algebraic compression of quantum circuits for Hamiltonian evolution, Kökcü E., Camps D.,
- **2022** Bassman L., Freericks J.K., de Jong W.A., Van Beeumen R., Kemper A.F., Phys. Rev. A,DOI:10.1103/PhysRevA.105.032420.
 - An algebraic quantum circuit compression algorithm for Hamiltonian simulation, Camps D.,
- **2021** Kökcü E., Bassman L., de Jong W.A., Kemper A.F., Van Beeumen R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 43(3), DOI:10.1137/21M1439298,arXiv:2108.03283.
- **A multishift, multipole rational QZ method with aggressive early deflation,** Steel T., Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 42(2), 753–774. DOI: 10.1137/19M1249631
- **Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings, Camps D.**, Van Beeumen R., Phys. Rev. A 102, 052411. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevA.102.052411
 - Chemistry on quantum computers with virtual quantum subspace expansion, Urbanek M.,
- **2020** Camps D., Van Beeumen R., de Jong W. A., J. Chem. Theory Comput. 16(9), 5425–5431. DOI: 10.1021/acs.jctc.0c00447
- **Quantum Fourier transform revisited, Camps D.**, Van Beeumen R., Yang C., Numer. Linear Algebra Appl. 28(1). DOI: 10.1002/nla.2331
- **On pole-swapping algorithms for the eigenvalue problem, Camps D.,** Mach T., Vandebril R., Watkins D. S., Electron. Trans. Numer. Anal. 52, 480–508. DOI: 10.1553/etna_vol52s480
- Swapping 2x2 blocks in the Schur and generalized Schur form, Camps D., Mastronardi N., Vandebril R., Van Dooren P., J. Comput. Appl. Math. 373. 112274. DOI: 10.1016/j.cam.2019.05.022
- 2019 *A rational QZ method*, Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 40(3), 943–972. DOI: 10.1137/18M1170480
- An implicit filter for rational Krylov using core transformations, Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., Linear Algebra and its Applications, DOI: 10.1016/j.laa.2018.09.021

 Block term decomposition for modelling epileptic seizures, Hunyadi B., Camps D., Sorber L.,
- **2014** Van Paesschen W., De Vos M., Van Huffel S., De Lathauwer L., EURASIP Journal on Advances in Signal Processing, DOI: 10.1186/1687-6180-2014-139

Education

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

PhD in Computer Science and Applied Mathematics

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2015 - Sep. 2019

- Thesis: *Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem Rational QR algorithms*.
- Generalized dense QR eigenvalue algorithms to rational QR methods.
- Implicitly restarted rational Krylov methods for large-scale, sparse eigenvalue problems.
- Focus on theory, numerical stability and efficient implementations.

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

M.Sc.Eng. in Mathematical Engineering

• Thesis: 'Epileptic seizure monitoring using tensor decomposition techniques'.

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2013

3

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

M.Sc. in Physics: Astronomy and Astrophysics

• Thesis: 'Heschel/PACS observations of water in the carbon-rich AGB star V Hya'.

UHasselt (University of Hasselt)

B.Sc. in Physics Sep. 2006 - Jun. 2010

Leuven, Belgium

Hasselt, Belgium

Virtual

Sep. 2009 - Sep. 2011

Talks

Teratec Workshop Reims, France June 2024

From HamLib to HamPerf: A Hamiltonian-Oriented Approach to Quantum Benchmarking

ISC High Performance 2024 Hamburg, Germany Evaluation of the classical hardware requirements for large-scale quantum computations May 2024

DW75 Workshop Leuven, Belgium

On Block Encodings of Matrices May 2024

APS March Meeting Minneapolis, MN, USA Exploring the Lieb lattice phase diagram using Rydberg atom quantum simulators March 2024

SC23 – The International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Denver, CO

Storage, and Analysis A Performance Model for Estimating the Cost of Scaling to Practical Quantum Advantage November 2023

Intel Labs Quantum Seminar Series

Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits September 2023

10th International Congress on Industrial and Applied Mathematics Tokyo, Japan FunFact: Tensor Decomposition, Your Way August 2023

Virtual IonQ Quantum Seminar Series

Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits May 2023

Guest lecture at San Francisco State University San Francisco, CA, USA

Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits *April 2023* Las Vegas, NV, USA APS March Meeting

Classical and Quantum Strategies to Boost Quantum Subspace Methods March 2023

IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering Broomfield, CO, USA

FABLE: Fast Approximate Quantum Circuits for Block-Encodings September 2022

XXI Householder Symposium on Numerical Linear Algebra Selva di Fasano, Italy An Algebraic Quantum Circuit Compression Algorithm for Hamiltonian Simulation June 2022

CS Area 3rd Annual Postdoc Symposium Berkeley, USA

FunFact: a Tensor Algebra Language with Applications in Deep Learning Feb. 2022

SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra Virtual Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings May 2021

AIDE-QC All-Hands Meeting Virtual

An Algebraic and Scalable Synthesis Algorithm for Computing Dynamic Simulation Apr. 2021

Constant-Depth Circuits APS March Meeting Virtual

Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings Mar. 2021

SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering Virtual Understanding the quantum Fourier transform through matrix decompositions Mar. 2021

QIP Conference Virtual (Munich, Germany)

Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings Feb. 2021

CS Area 2nd Annual Postdoc Symposium Berkeley, USA Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings Feb. 2021

Berkeley Lab Seminar Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem – Rational QR algorithms	Berkeley, USA Sep. 2019
ICIAM Conference Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem – Rational QR algorithms	Valencia, Spain Jul. 2019
ETNA25 Conference Approximate inverse-free rational Krylov methods and the link with FOM and GMRES	Sardinia, Italy May 2019
NASCA Conference A rational QZ method	Kalamata, Greece Jul. 2018
SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra RQZ: A rational QZ method for the generalized eigenvalue problem	Hong Kong May. 2018
NUMA Internal Seminar Rational matrix algorithms for the generalized eigenvalue problem — Iterative and direct methods	Leuven, Belgium Oct. 2017
ILAS Conference	Iowa, USA
Implicit restart of the rational Krylov method — Chasing algorithms for polynomial, extended and rational Krylov	Jul. 2017
ILAS Conference Towards a computational efficient, implicitly restarted rational Krylov method	Leuven, Belgium Jul. 2016
Academic service	

IOP New Journal of Physics, ACM Transactions on Quantum Computing, IEEE

Transactions on Quantum Engineering, npj Quantum Information, Quantum – the open

journal for quantum science, Quantum Information & Computation, Journal of

Reviewer for

Computational Physics, Applied Mathematics and Computation, SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications, Linear and Multilinear Algebra, Electronic Transactions on Numerical Analysis, IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering

Program Committee for IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering 2022 & 2024

Honors & Awards

2024 Hans Meuer Award for Best Research Paper, ISC High Performance.

Hamburg, Germany Hong Kong

2018 *SIAM Student Travel Award*, SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra.